<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of peace and alliance between the most serene and mighty prince, Charles II. By the grace of God king of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. and the high and mighty lords, the States General of the United Netherlands, concluded the 14th day of September, 1662. / Published by his Majesties command.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2896A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223293</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175793</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2751:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles of peace and alliance between the most serene and mighty prince, Charles II. By the grace of God king of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. and the high and mighty lords, the States General of the United Netherlands, concluded the 14th day of September, 1662. / Published by his Majesties command.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Commerce --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175793:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES OF <hi>PEACE</hi> and <hi>ALLIANCE</hi> Between the moſt Serene and Mighty PRINCE, CHARLES II. By the grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the <hi>High and Mighty LORDS,</hi> THE STATES GENERAL Of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITED NETHERLANDS,</hi> Concluded the 14<hi rend="sup">th,</hi> day of <hi>September,</hi> 1662.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:175793:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175793:2"/>
            <head>Articles of Peace and Alliance between the moſt Serene and Mighty Prince, <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, by the grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the High and Mighty Lords, the States General of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Netherlands,</hi> concluded the fourth day of <hi>September, 1662.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt it is concluded and agreed, That from henceforward there be a true, firm and inviolable Peace, ſincere Friendſhip and ſtraiter Alliance, Confederation and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between His Majeſty, the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the States General of the United Provinces of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and the reſpective Lands, Countries and Cities under their obedience, whereſoever ſcituate, and their People and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of what quality or condition ſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and the ſaid States General remain Friends, Confederate, United and Allied, for the defence and preſervation of the Rights, Liberties and Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of either Ally and their Subjects againſt all whomſoever, who ſhall endeavour to diſturb the Peace of eithers State by Sea or Land, or ſuch as living within eithers Dominions, ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared publick enemies to either.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:175793:3"/>
            <p n="3">III. That neither the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> nor the ſaid States General ſhall act, do, endeavour, treat or attempt any thing againſt the other, or the Subjects of either, any where by Land or Sea, or in any Ports, Liberties, Creeks or Freſh-waters, upon any occaſion whatſoever; And that neither they nor the Subjects of either of them, ſhall give, afford or ſupply any aid, counſel or favour, nor conſent that any thing be done, treated or attempted by any other whoſoever, to the harm or prejudice of the other, or the Subjects of either; but ſhall expreſly and actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſe, contradict, and really hinder all whomſoever, reſiding or dwelling in either the reſpective Dominions, who ſhall act, do treat or attempt any thing againſt either of them.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That neither the ſaid King nor the ſaid Common-wealth, nor any of the Subjects of either, inhabiting or reſiding under either of their Juriſdictions, ſhall encourage or aſſiſt with counſel, aid or favour, the Rebels of either; but ſhall expreſly and effectually hinder all perſons abiding, reſiding or dwelling in either of their Dominions, or under their Command, from ſending or furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under-hand to any of the aforeſaid Rebels, any ſuccour or aſſiſtance, either in Men, Ships, Arms, Ammunition or other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Goods, as alſo Money or Victuals; And that all Ships, Arms, Ammunition of War, or other contraband Goods, alſo Money or Victuals of any perſon or perſons whatſoever, which ſhall be ſent or imployed againſt the intent of this Article, ſhall be confiſcate and forfeited to the benefit of that ſide where the Offenders ſhall be found: And moreover, the perſons who wittingly and willingly ſhall have acted, undertaken, or given counſel againſt the ſenſe of this Article, ſhall be accounted ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of either Party, and ſhall be puniſhed as Traitors againſt the State where the offence ſhall be committed, But as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpecification of prohibited or contraband Goods, it ſhall be hereafter provided.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid States General ſhall mutually, ſincerely, and faithfully (as there is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) aſſiſt each other againſt the Rebels of either, by Sea or Land, with Men and Ships, at the coſt and charges of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties who deſire the ſame, in ſuch proportion and manner, and upon ſuch conditions, as afterward ſhall be agreed, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion ſhall require.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:175793:3"/>
            <p n="6">VI. That neither the ſaid King, nor the ſaid Common-wealth, nor the Subjects of either, ſhall in any of their Juriſdictions, Countries, Lands, Havens, Sea-ports, Creeks, receive any Rebel or Rebels, Fugitive or Fugitives of the other Party, declared, or to be declared, nor ſhall give or yield unto ſuch declared Rebels and Fugitives in the places aforeſaid, or elſewhere, though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Lands, Countries, Havens, Sea-ports, Creeks or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, and Help, Counſel, Lodging, Souldiers, Ships, Money, Arms, Ammunition or Victuals: As alſo neither of the States ſhall permit that ſuch Rebels or Fugitives be received by any perſon or perſons within their Juriſdictions, Countries, Lands, Sea-ports, Havens, Creeks, nor ſuffer that any Help, Counſel, Lodging, Favour, Arms, Ammunition, Souldiers, Ships, Moneys or Proviſion be given or yielded to ſuch Rebels and Fugitives; but ſhall expreſly and effectually oppoſe, and really hinder the ſame.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That in caſe either of them by their publick and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Letters ſhall make known and declare unto the other, that any perſon or perſons are or have been a Rebel or Rebels, Fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or Fugitives, and that they or any of them have been receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or reſide, lie hid, or ſeek ſhelter in their Juriſdictions, Lands, Countries, Sea-ports, or in any of them; then that party who ſhall have received ſuch Letters, or to whom ſuch notice ſhall be given, or declaration made, ſhall within the ſpace of Twenty eight dayes, to be accounted from the day that ſuch notice was given, be bound to Charge and Command ſuch Rebel or Rebels, Fugitive or Fugitives to withdraw and depart out of their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, Lands, Dominions, Countries, and every of them: And in caſe any of the ſaid Rebels or Fugitives do not withdraw and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part within fifteen dayes after ſuch Charge or Command ſo given, then that they be puniſhed with death, and loſs of Lands &amp; Goods.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. That no Rebel of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> ſhall be received into any of the Caſtles, Cities, Havens, Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, or other places Priviledg'd or not Priviledg'd which any perſon, of what dignity or degree ſoever he be, or ſhall be, hath within the Dominions or Territories of the United Provinces, by what right or title ſoever he doth or ſhall hold or poſſeſs the ſame; nor be permitted to be received into, or
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175793:4"/>remain in them, by any perſon, of what quality or degree ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be. Neither ſhall the ſaid States General permit or ſuffer, that in any of the aforeſaid places, any Aſſiſtance, Counſel or favour with Ships, Souldiers, Money or Proviſion, or in any other manner, be given or afforded unto any ſuch Rebel, by any perſon of what degree or quality ſoever he be, but ſhall openly and expreſly forbid, and effectually hinder the ſame. And if any perſon or perſons, of what degree or quality ſoever they be, dwelling or remaining within the Dominions of the ſaid United Provinces, or under their Command, ſhall act any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Agreement, That then all and ſingular ſuch perſons ſo doing, ſhall for term of their lives reſpectively, loſe and forfeit all ſuch Caſtles, Towns, Villages, Lands, and other places which they or any of them at that time have or pretend to have, by what right or title ſoever. In like manner, no Rebel of the ſaid States of the United Provinces ſhall be received into any Caſtles, Towns, Havens, or other places, or any of them, Priviledg'd, or not priviledg'd, which any perſon or perſons, of what degree or quality ſoever they be, and by what right or title ſoever he or they do or ſhall hold and poſſeſs, within the Kingdoms or Dominions of His ſaid Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain:</hi> Nor ſhall ſuch Rebel be ſuffered to be received by any perſon or perſons whatſoever, or there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main; neither ſhall the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> permit or ſuffer, that any Counſel, Aſſiſtance, or Favour in any of the ſaid Places with Ships, Men, Money, Victuals, or in any other manner be given or afforded unto any ſuch Rebel, by any ſuch perſon or perſons, of what degree or quality ſoever they be, but ſhall openly and expreſly forbid, and effectually hinder the ſame. And in caſe any of the Subjects of the ſaid King, or within His Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſhall do or attempt any thing againſt this Agreement, That all and every perſons ſo offending, ſhall in like manner for their reſpective lives, loſe and forfeit all ſuch Caſtles, Cities, Towns, Lands, and other places which they or any of them at that time hath, or ſhall pretend to have, by any right or title whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. That the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and His Subjects, and all the Inhabitants of His Majeſties Dominions, and alſo the ſaid United Provinces and their Subjects and Inhabitants, of what rank or condition ſoever they be, ſhall be bound
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175793:4"/>to uſe each other kindly and friendly in every thing; ſo that they may freely and ſafely paſs by land or by water into each others Countries, Cities, Towns walled or unwalled, fortified or not fortified, and their Havens, and all other their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſcituate in <hi>Europe,</hi> to continue and abide therein, ſo long as they ſhall pleaſe, and may there buy ſo much Proviſions as are neceſſary for their uſe, without any hinderance: And that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they may Trade and Traffique in Goods and Commodities of all ſorts, as to them ſhall ſeem fit, and then to Export and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port at their pleaſure, paying the uſual Duties, ſaving to each Countrey their particular Laws and Cuſtoms. Provided that the Subjects and Inhabitants of either ſide exerciſing their Trade in each others Countries and Dominions, ſhall not be obliged hereafter to pay any more Cuſtoms, Impoſt, or other Duties, then according to that proportion which other Foreign Nations Trading in the ſaid places do uſually pay.</p>
            <p n="10">X. That the Ships and Veſſels of the ſaid United Provinces, as well men of War as others, meeting any Men of War of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain's</hi> in the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Seas, ſhall Strike the Flag, and Lore the Top-ſail in ſuch manner as the ſame hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly obſerved in any times whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. And for the greater freedom of Commerce and Navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is agreed and concluded, That the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid States General, ſhall not receive into their Havens, Cities and Towns, nor ſuffer that any of the Subjects or Inhabitants of either ſide do receive Pirates or Sea-Rovers, or afford them any entertainment, aſſiſtance, or proviſion, but ſhall endeavour that the ſaid Pirates and Sea-Rovers, or their Partners, Sharers and Abettors, be found out, apprehended, and ſuffer condign puniſhment for the terror of others; And all the Ships, Goods, and Commodities taken by them in Piracy, and brought into the Havens of either Dominion, ſuch Goods as can be found, although they were ſold, ſhall be reſtored to the right Owners, or ſatisfaction given to them, or to ſuch perſons as ſhall claim them by Letters of Procuration, ſo as the property be made to appear in the Court of Admiralty by due and lawfull Evidence.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. It ſhall not be permitted to the Subjects of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the Inhabitants of the Kingdoms and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175793:5"/>Countries under His Obedience, or to the Inhabitants and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the ſaid United Provinces, to do or offer any Hoſtility or Violence to each other, either by Land or by Sea, upon any pretence or colour whatſoever: And conſequently it ſhall not be lawfull for the ſaid Subjects or Inhabitants to get Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions or Letters of Repriſal from any Prince or State, with whom either of the Confederates are at difference, or in open War; and much leſs by vertue of thoſe Letters to moleſt or damnifie the Subjects of either Party. Neither ſhall it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any Foreign private Men of War, who are not Subjects to one or the other Party, having Commiſſions from any other Prince or State, to Equip their Ships in the Harbours of either of the aforeſaid Parties, or to ſell or ranſom their prizes, or any other way to Truck, as well the Ships and Goods, as any other Loading whatſoever. And it ſhall not be lawfull for them to buy any Victual, but what ſhall be neceſſary to bring them to the next Port of that Prince from whom they obtained their ſaid Commiſſions. And if perchance any of the Subjects of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> or of the ſaid States General ſhall buy, or get to themſelves by Truck, or any other way, ſuch Ship or Goods which have been taken by the Subjects of one or the other Party; in ſuch caſe the ſaid Subjects ſhall be bound to reſtore the ſaid Ship or Goods to the Proprietors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay, and without any Compenſation or re-imburſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Money paid or promiſed for the ſame; Provided that they make it appear before the Council of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> or before the ſaid States General, that they are the right Owners or Proprietors of them.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. That in caſe the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> or the ſaid States General do make any Treaty of Amity or Alliance with any other Kings, Re-publicks, Princes or States, they ſhall therein comprehend each other and their Dominions, if they deſire to be therein comprehended; and ſhall give to the other notice of all ſuch Treaties of Friendſhip and Alliance.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. That in caſe it happen, during this Friendſhip, Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy and Alliance, any thing ſhall be done or attempted by any of the Subjects or Inhabitants of either Party againſt this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or any part thereof, by Land, Sea or Freſh-waters, That never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:175793:5"/>this Amity and Alliance between the ſaid Nations ſhall not thereby be broken or interrupted, but ſhall remain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in its full force; and that only thoſe particular perſons ſhall be puniſhed, who have committed any thing againſt this Treaty, and none elſe; and that Juſtice ſhall be rendred, and ſatisfaction given to all perſons concerned, by all ſuch who have committed any thing contrary to this Treaty, by land or ſea, or other waters, in any part of <hi>Europe,</hi> or any places within the <hi>Straits,</hi> or in <hi>America,</hi> or upon the Coaſts of <hi>Africa,</hi> or in any Lands, Iſlands, Seas, Creeks, Bayes, Rivers, or in any pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on this ſide the <hi>Cape of Good Hope,</hi> within twelve moneths ſpace after Juſtice ſhall be demanded; And in all places whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever on the other ſide the ſaid <hi>Cape</hi> (as hath been aboveſaid) within eighteen moneths next enſuing after demand of Juſtice ſhall be made in maner aforeſaid. But in caſe the offenders againſt this Treaty do not appear and ſubmit themſelves to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and give ſatisfaction within the reſpective times above ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, proportionable to the diſtance of the places, they ſhall be declared enemies of both Parties, and their Eſtates, Goods and Revenues whatſoever, ſhall be confiſcated for due and full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the injuries and wrongs by them offered; and their perſons alſo, when they come within the Dominions of either Party, ſhall be liable unto ſuch puniſhments as every one ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for his reſpective offences.</p>
            <p n="15">XV. It is alſo agreed and concluded between His ſaid Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid Lords States of the United <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands,</hi> That the Iſland of <hi>Pularon</hi> ſhall be reſtored unto His ſaid Majeſty, or unto them whom He ſhall thereunto appoint by a Commiſſion under the great Seal of <hi>England;</hi> and that ſo ſoon as any one provided with ſuch a Commiſſion, ſhall arrive there and demand the ſaid reſtitution: Which that it may be effected with the more eaſe and certainty, Commiſsions neceſſary for that end ſhall be delivered unto Him from the States General and the <hi>Netherlands Eaſt India</hi> Company, immediatly after the Ratification of this Treaty. And that by the reſtitution of the ſaid Iſland of <hi>Pularon,</hi> all actions and pretenſions wherein the Subjects of either Party think they have right for loſſes, injuries and offences committed upon each other in <hi>India,</hi> and taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175793:6"/>of in <hi>England</hi> before the 10th,/20. of <hi>January,</hi> 1658/9. (with this exception, That they who ſay that they have ſuffered loſs in two Ships, to wit, the <hi>Bonaventure</hi> and <hi>Bona Eſperanza,</hi> may proſecute the Suit already begun) ſhall ceaſe, be extinguiſhed and annulled in the maner following:</p>
            <p>That all offences, injuries and loſſes (except before excepted) which one part hath ſuffered, or can any way pretend to have ſuffered from the other in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> whereof any notice hath been given to the Engliſh at <hi>London,</hi> or to the <hi>Netherlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> at the <hi>Hague,</hi> before the twentieth day of <hi>January,</hi> 1659. new Stile, or the tenth of <hi>January,</hi> 1658. old Stile; but in other parts of the world on this ſide the <hi>Cape,</hi> of any actions or things whatſoever, that hapned before the publication and notice of the Peace concluded between both Nations the 4/14. day of <hi>March,</hi> 1653/4. ſhall remain utterly cancelled and extinguiſhed, ſo as neither Party ſhall trouble the other for any ſuch damage, offence, injury or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment (except before excepted) but there ſhall be and remain a perfect abolition of all and every one of them, and all Suits and Actions upon ſuch account ſhall be void and null: But other da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, offences, injuries and detriments, which the Engliſh Nation either upon publick or private account, can affirm to have fallen or been brought upon them by the Government of the United <hi>Netherlands,</hi> or by the Companies or private perſons ſubject to that Government; as on the other ſide what the United <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlanders</hi> can, upon publick or private account, pretend to have fallen or been brought upon them by the Government of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or by the Companies or private perſons ſubject there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> before the 10th./20, day of <hi>January,</hi> 1658/9. or at leaſt whereof there was no notice at <hi>London</hi> or the <hi>Hague,</hi> before that day; and in other parts of the world after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication and notice of the aforeſaid Peace in the year, 1653/4, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further diſtinction or exception of perſons, place or time, ſhall be ſubmitted, as by this Treaty they are ſubmitted, unto the examination, arbitration and deciſion of Commiſsioners or Arbitrators, after the maner and under the conditions following.</p>
            <p>That Commiſſioners be appointed only for maters paſt, but not at all for matters to come, which may happen after the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Treaty is concluded.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:175793:6"/>
            <p>That their Commiſsion directed unto paſt things only, as hath been already ſaid, is not to contain any general Clauſe, but to be expreſſely confined and limited to a ſpecial Catalogue, which ſhall be annexed unto the Commiſsion, ſo as they may by no means take cogniſance of any other thing beſides the Actions ſet down in that Catalogue.</p>
            <p>But that they may mutually agree thereupon, a Catalogue ſhall be made by both Parties, and interchangably delivered, that it may be punctually and duly examined by either ſide: And if there be found in either of the Catalogues, any thing whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever relating to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> which were known in <hi>London</hi> before the 10th./20. of <hi>January,</hi> 1658/9 as to actions of the Engliſh, or at the ſame time at the <hi>Hague,</hi> as to the actions of the United Provinces, or which hapned in other parts of the world before the publication and notice of the foreſaid Peace; in the year, 1653/4 or other actions of ſuch a nature as may not be thought fit to be referred unto ſuch Arbitration, they ſhall be rejected and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punged out of the Catalogues.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, after each ſide is agreed upon theſe Catalogues, a whole year ſhall be appointed, wherein all buſineſſes contained in in thoſe Catalogues may be accommodated and compoſed by friendly conferences between His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Miniſter and the Commiſſioners of the States General at the <hi>Hague;</hi> and the Pretenders or their Deputies thereunto appointed by ſpecial Letters of Atturney, ſhall be bound to make their appearance at the <hi>Hague,</hi> before the end of the ſixth moneth in the foreſaid year: But that year being expired, all thoſe actions about which the Pretenders or their Deputies were at the <hi>Hague</hi> with an aim or purpoſe to have them brought unto a friendly iſſue (which they ſhall be bound to prove by a lawfull teſtimony of the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s Envoy, and the Commiſſioners of the States General, or of either of them) and which nevertheleſs have not been by that time brought to ſuch an iſſue, ſhall be referred to the ſaid Commiſsioners, that they may be at laſt compoſed or decided by them; which Commiſsioners, after the ſaid year is expired, if there remain any Actions uncompoſed in ſuch friendly maner at that time, ſhall to that purpoſe meet at <hi>London,</hi> and they ſhall be four on either ſide, inſtructed and provided with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:175793:7"/>and thenceforward this ſubmiſsion and progreſs in and through all things, ſhall be carried on in the ſame manner as it was in the year 1654. But ſo as the Arbitration upon theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters be not referred to the Proteſtant Cantons of <hi>Swiſſerland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">XVI. That the Subjects of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and thoſe which are under His Juriſdiction, may freely and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely travel in all the Provinces of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and all their Dominions in <hi>Europe,</hi> and through them by Sea or Land paſs to other places there or beyond them, and through all Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the United Provinces, Cities, Forts, or Gariſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, which are in any parts of the United Provinces, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in their Dominions in <hi>Europe,</hi> as well they themſelves exerciſing Trade in all thoſe places, as their Agents, Factors and Servants, may go armed or unarmed (but if armed, not above Forty in a Company) as well without their Goods and Merchandiſes as with them, whereſoever they pleaſe. The People alſo and Inhabitants of the United Provinces ſhall enjoy the ſame liberty and Freedom in all the Dominions of the ſaid King in <hi>Europe;</hi> Provided that they and every of them do in their Trade and Merchandiſing yield obedience to the Laws and Statutes of either Nation reſpectively.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. That in caſe the Merchant-Ships of the Subjects of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their Nation ſhall by Storm, Pirates, or any other neceſsity what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, be driven into any Haven of either Dominion, they may depart ſecurely and at their pleaſure, with their Ships and Goods, without paying any Cuſtoms or other Duties; provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they break no Bulk, nor ſell any thing; nor ſhall they be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any Moleſtation or Search, provided they do not receive on board any Perſons or Goods, nor do any thing elſe contrary to the Laws, Ordinances or Cuſtoms of the places where they (as aforeſaid) ſhall happen to arrive.</p>
            <p n="18">XVIII. That the Merchants, Maſters and Seamen of either Party, their Ships, Goods, Wares, or Merchandiſes ſhall not be Arreſted or Seiſed in the Lands, Havens, Roads or Rivers of the other, to ſerve at War, or any other uſe, by vertue of any general or ſpecial Command, unleſs upon an extraordinary ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, and that juſt ſatisfaction be given for the ſame; but ſo as the ſame ſhall not derogate from the Seiſures and Arreſts
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:175793:7"/>duely made in the ordinary Courts of Juſtice of either Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. That the Merchants on both ſides, their Factors and Servants, and alſo the Maſters and other Seamen, as well going as returning by Sea and other Waters, as alſo in the Havens of either Party, or going on Shore, may carry and uſe for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of themſelves and Goods, all forts of Weapons, as well Offenſive as Defenſive; but being come into their Lodgings or Inns, they ſhall there lay by and leave their Arms, until they be going on board again.</p>
            <p n="20">XX. That the Men of War, or Convoys of either Nation, meeting or overtaking at Sea any Merchants Ship or Ships belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Subjects or Inhabitants of the other, holding the ſame Courſe, or going the ſame Way, ſhall be bound, as long as they keep one Courſe together, to protect and defend them againſt all and every one who would ſet upon them.</p>
            <p n="21">XXI. That if any Ship or Ships of the Subjects or Inhabitants of either Nation, or of a Neuter, be taken by a third Party in the Harbours of either, not being of the Subjects or Inhabitants of either Nation, they, in or out of whoſe Haven or Juriſdiction the ſaid Ships ſhall be taken, ſhall be bound to endeavour with the other Party, that the ſaid Ship or Ships be purſued, brought back, and reſtored to the Owners; but all this ſhall be done at the charges of the Owners, or whom it concerns.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. That Searchers and other like Officers on both ſides, ſhall regulate themſelves according to the Laws of either Nation, and ſhall not impoſe or demand more then they are allowed by their Commiſſions and Inſtructions.</p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. That if any injury be done or practiſed by either Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the Subjects or Inhabitants of the ſame, againſt the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects or Inhabitants of the other, or againſt any of the Articles of this preſent, Treaty, or againſt common right; yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs no Letters of Repriſal, Mark or Countermark ſhall be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by either ſide, till Juſtice hath been firſt demanded according to the ordinary courſe of Law; but in caſe Juſtice be there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied or delayed, then that the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> and the ſaid States General, or Commiſſioners of that Nation whoſe Subjects and Inhabitants have ſuffered the wrong, ſhall publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:175793:8"/>require Juſtice from that other Party, where (as above-ſaid) it was denied or delayed, or from that Power appointed to heat and decide ſuch differences, that there may be a friendly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, or due proceſs of Law. But if ſtill there happen more delays, and neither Juſtice be adminiſtred, nor ſatisfaction given within three moneths after ſuch demand, that then Letters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſal, Mark, or Countermark may be granted.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. That they who have obtained private Commiſsions from either Party, before they receive ſuch Commiſsions, ſhall give good and ſufficient caution before the Judge of the Court where they receive ſuch Commiſsions, by reſponſible men, who have no part or ſhare in ſuch Ships, that they ſhall do no damage or injury to the Subjects or Inhabitants of either ſide.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. It is alſo agreed and concluded, That the Subjects and Inhabitants of either Party ſhall alwayes have free acceſs to each others Sea-ports, there to remain and from thence to depart with the ſame freedom; and not only with their Merchant-ſhips and Loading, but alſo with their Men of War, whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the ſaid King or States General, or unto ſuch as have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained private Commiſsions, whether they arrive through vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of tempeſt or other caſualty of the Seas, or to mend their Ships, or to buy Proviſion, ſo they exceed not the number of eight Men of War when they come there voluntarily, nor ſhall remain or abide longer in the Havens or Places adjacent, then they ſhall have a juſt cauſe to repair their ſaid Ships, or to buy Victuals or other neceſſaries. And if a greater number of Men of War ſhould upon occaſion deſire to come unto ſuch Ports, they ſhall in no caſe enter thereinto, untill they have firſt obtained leave from thoſe to whom the ſaid Havens do appertain, unleſs they be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſo to do by ſtorm, or ſome force or neceſsity, whereby they may avoid the danger of the Sea: In which caſe alſo they ſhall preſently make known the cauſe of their coming unto the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour or chief Magiſtrate of the place, and ſhall ſtay no longer then the ſaid Governour or chief Magiſtrate ſhall permit them, and ſhall not do any acts of Hoſtility or other prejudice in the aforeſaid Havens during their abode there.</p>
            <p n="26">XXVI. Furthermore it is agreed and concluded, That both Parties ſhall truly and firmly obſerve and execute this preſent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:175793:8"/>Treaty, and all and every the maters contained therein, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually cauſe the ſame to be obſerved and performed by the Subjects and Inhabitants of either Nation.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. Alſo for further caution and aſſurance that this Treaty and Confederacy ſhall be duly and <hi>bonâ fide</hi> obſerved on the part of the ſaid States General of the United Provinces and their People, it is concluded and agreed, as alſo the ſaid States General by theſe preſents do agree, and firmly oblige and bind themſelves, That all and every one whom they or the States of the Provinces ſhall at any time chooſe, appoint, or make Captain General, Governour or chief Preſident, or State-holder, General of Armies or Military Forces by Land, or Admiral or General of the Fleets, Ships or Forces at Sea, ſhall be bound and obliged by Oath to confirm this Treaty and all the Articles thereof, and promiſe ſacredly upon Oath, that they ſhall, as far as it is poſſible, religiouſly obſerve and execute the ſame, and as much as concerns them, cauſe the ſame be obſerved and executed by others.</p>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. And it is further agreed and concluded, That this preſent Treaty, and all and every thing therein contained and concluded, ſhall be confirmed and ratified by the ſaid King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid States General of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, by Letters Patents on both ſides, ſealed with the great Seal, in due and authentick form, within three moneths next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, (or ſooner if it can be done) and that within the ſaid time the Ratifications on both ſides ſhall be exchanged; and that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the delivery and exchange, this Treaty and Alliance ſhall be publiſhed in ſuch places and maner as is uſual.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Re-printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
